<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The frog, or, The Low-Countrey nightingale, sweet singer of Amsterdam The Old Exchange to the New Stat-House hoping fair acceptance, a speedy and handsome return, this true fable dedicates.</title>
            <title>Holland nightingale.</title>
            <author>Ogilby, John, 1600-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O172B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826176</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1822:7, 1766:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The frog, or, The Low-Countrey nightingale, sweet singer of Amsterdam The Old Exchange to the New Stat-House hoping fair acceptance, a speedy and handsome return, this true fable dedicates.</title>
                  <title>Holland nightingale.</title>
                  <author>Ogilby, John, 1600-1676.</author>
                  <author>Aesop.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 7, [1] p. : ill. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>167-]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Ogilby.</note>
                  <note>Published in 1672 as: Holland nightingale.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Based in part on Aesop's fable LXXXII.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing A729B (number cancelled) on UMI microfilm set "Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 1822.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:30568:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <figure>
               <p>D D D<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:30568:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <p>THE FROG, OR, The Low-Countrey NIGHTINGALE, Sweet Singer of AMSTERDAM.</p>
            <p>THE OLD EXCHANGE TO THE NEW STAT-HOUSE, Hoping fair Acceptance, a Speedy and handſome Return, This true FABLE DEDICATES.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb facs="tcp:30568:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30568:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
            <head>AESOP, FAB. LXXXII.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>OF THE FROGS</hi> Fearing the S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N ſhould Marry.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ow-Countrey Provinces, United Bogs,</l>
               <l>Once diſtreſt States, now <hi>Hogen Mogen</hi> Frogs;</l>
               <l>Royal and Noble Intereſt gone, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</l>
               <l>Grown formidable both at Sea and Land:</l>
               <l>Who but a Century of years before</l>
               <l>Dabbled in Fiſhing, deſpicably Poor,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:30568:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
               <l>In ſeamleſs Veſſels, Troughs, cut out of Logs,</l>
               <l>Catch'd Whiting-Mops; now <hi>Gogs</hi> and <hi>Gogmagogs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In ſtately Pines new Conſtellations raiſe,</l>
               <l>Ploughing up Billows two and thirty ways;</l>
               <l>Through boyling Brine, through Cakes of cruſted Ice,</l>
               <l>For Gold and Silver, Ivory, Oyl, and Spice;</l>
               <l>What Straights, Gulphs, trending Bays, ſpare they to pierce,</l>
               <l>By Water to take in the Univerſe?</l>
               <l>Are they with Force not able to invade?</l>
               <l>No matter; They'l undo the World by Trade:</l>
               <l>Four Frogs, two Tod-pols, and one greaſy Toad,</l>
               <l>Deep freighted Bottoms bear from Road to Road.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whom now a conſternating Panick Fear</l>
               <l>Dejected much: The Sun will wed they hear;</l>
               <l>The News from <hi>India,</hi> worſe than Plague or War,</l>
               <l>Brought and atteſted by the Blazing Star.</l>
               <l>To Pigmy Inches theſe Gygantick Frogs,</l>
               <l>Pale Terror, ſhrunk: Summon'd from all the Bogs,</l>
               <l>Hopping or crawling they in Cluſters came</l>
               <l>Up to their Prime <hi>Morraſs,</hi> their greateſt <hi>Damm.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There the new State-houſe ſtands, built fair and large,</l>
               <l>For their own Profit, but the Peoples Charge;</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30568:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
               <l>Where they on all Emergencies of State,</l>
               <l>Or Private buſineſs, in Convention ſate:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No <hi>Portico</hi> this Modern Building fac'd,</l>
               <l>Within no antient Princes figures grac'd;</l>
               <l>Nor Grandſires with their Nets, ſuch were too Poor</l>
               <l>To ſtand with Beſoms there behind the Door,</l>
               <l>Who for their own <hi>Good-Old-Cauſe</hi> Martyrs dy'd</l>
               <l>By Hemp, or by more zealous Fagots try'd.</l>
               <l>But Gods and Goddeſſes in Marble Carv'd,</l>
               <l>Or finely Painted, which the Heathen ſerv'd,</l>
               <l>In all the <hi>Nieches,</hi> each convenient Place</l>
               <l>In Stone or Tables the fair Structure grace;</l>
               <l>But yet for all their Skill, theſe Belgick Toads</l>
               <l>Made <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſie-Dutch</hi> Heroes and Grecian Gods.</l>
               <l>Early this day aſſembled Old and Young</l>
               <l>The <hi>Damm</hi> they cover, and the State-houſe throng;</l>
               <l>Silence commanded, not one whiſpering Croak,</l>
               <l>An old Sag-bellied Toad riſing, thus ſpoke:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grave <hi>Hogen Mogens,</hi> High and Mighty Frogs!</l>
               <l>Whoſe Care and Prudence fertiliz'd theſe Bogs,</l>
               <l>And ſo improv'd theſe your United States,</l>
               <l>Princes to Beard, and be with Kings <hi>Cope-Mates;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:30568:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
               <l>Though we from Muſhroms ſprung, and Spawn of Toads,</l>
               <l>Like Palaces are now our fair Aboads;</l>
               <l>When through brack Waters, and a ſalt <hi>Morraſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We in cut Trenches ſafe at pleaſure paſs,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Damm</hi> to <hi>Damm,</hi> and time with Talk beguile,</l>
               <l>Our ſelves and goods landing 'thout Care or Toyl;</l>
               <l>From which new Water-works more Rent you raiſe,</l>
               <l>Than from rank Acres, where fat Oxen graſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But what of theſe Improvements will become?</l>
               <l>The Sun will Wed, and Nuptials keep at Home;</l>
               <l>Whom Laws of Gods and Men allow a year</l>
               <l>From War or Travel, with his fair Compeer;</l>
               <l>His Abſence will our Marſhes in a trice</l>
               <l>To Cryſtal turn, a never-thawing Ice.</l>
               <l>Or ſhould we ſcape ſuch a continued Froſt</l>
               <l>As guirdles up nine Months the Artick Coaſt,</l>
               <l>His teeming Spouſe may yet produce a Son,</l>
               <l>Shall quite out of the beaten <hi>Zodiack</hi> run,</l>
               <l>So un-experienc'd drive his Father's Chair,</l>
               <l>That ſoon to Fire he'll rarefie the Air,</l>
               <l>Water and Earth to Duſt and Aſhes turn,</l>
               <l>And all in one new Conflagration burn.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30568:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <lg>
               <l>They tell how <hi>Phaeton</hi> our ample Bogs</l>
               <l>To Jelly boyl'd; ſtew'd Tod-pols, Toads, and Frogs</l>
               <l>In one Potage, and <hi>Pluto</hi> gave, who ſwore</l>
               <l>He never taſted Broth ſo Rich before.</l>
               <l>Many ſuch Yonkers may ſpring from his Loyns,</l>
               <l>And ſhare his Houſes twelve Celeſtial Signs;</l>
               <l>And they may Wed, have Sons, and Daughters too:</l>
               <l>What in this Imminent Danger ſhall we do!</l>
               <l>To what Protector ſhall we make addreſs?</l>
               <l>All know that <hi>Neptune</hi> this concerns no leſs;</l>
               <l>Such drinking Suns may at one meeting Quaff,</l>
               <l>If he had twenty Plumbleſs Oceans, off.</l>
               <l>Him to implore lay by next Sabbath day,</l>
               <l>We're no ſuch Jews nor Chriſtians but we may:</l>
               <l>He heard us lately, when a ſwelling Tide</l>
               <l>Imbodied, threaten'd o'r our Tow'rs to ride;</l>
               <l>And ſoon as mov'd, with his great Trident came,</l>
               <l>Beats off green Reg'ments ſtorm'd our yielding <hi>Dam;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which had they batter'd but nine Inches higher,</l>
               <l>We had not liv'd, ruin to fear by Fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, Oh wondrous! the Foundations quake,</l>
               <l>And the ſtiff Idols, fixt in Marble, ſhake;</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:30568:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
               <l>When <hi>Neptune,</hi> where he did in Triumph ride,</l>
               <l>On a rich Shell, his Cheeks freſh Sanguine dy'd,</l>
               <l>His Trident waving then with Arms diſplai'd,</l>
               <l>Thus to the great Convention, wondring, ſaid;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Batavian</hi> Frogs, advanc'd by my ſole Power,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Jove</hi> firſt planted from a Thunder ſhower,</l>
               <l>Fear not the Sun, nor at his Of-ſpring ſhake:</l>
               <l>To the laſt drop I'll drain my ample Lake,</l>
               <l>My watery Kingdoms Laver into Suds,</l>
               <l>To quench their Torches; to the <hi>Stygian</hi> Floods</l>
               <l>I'll <hi>Titan</hi> ſend, and all his fiery Tits,</l>
               <l>To light their Lamps, and to regain their Wits.</l>
               <l>Lay idle Fears aſide, he'll never Wed,</l>
               <l>Nor plant a Female in a flaming Bed.</l>
               <l>Suſpect no Conflagrations from the Eaſt;</l>
               <l>But a new Sun now riſing in the Weſt;</l>
               <l>His Flames beware, make Peace, or Arm with ſpeed;</l>
               <l>You more then all the Elements will need:</l>
               <l>Call our Supernal, Call th' Infernal Liſt,</l>
               <l>Both Gods and Fiends too weak are to reſiſt:</l>
               <l>He threatens my large Arms to bind in Chains,</l>
               <l>And now at Home a ſecond <hi>Neptune</hi> reigns;</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:30568:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
               <l>Who three great Nations ſwaies, and two fair Iſles,</l>
               <l>His People <hi>Ruler of the Ocean</hi> ſtiles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, their God grows pale, Limbs ſtiff and cold,</l>
               <l>Trembling with Fear, ſhrunk in their Marble Mold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>MORAL.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Princes beware to aid a growing State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leſt they be firſt that give you the Check-Mate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wealth and Succeſs turns Humbleneſs to Pride:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beggars on Horſ-back to the Devil ride.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30568:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
